S2 Module 4: RISC-V ZKVMs with Uma Roy
Tracy: Hello, welcome to ZK Whiteboard Sessions.
We're doing a module today on RISC-V zkVMs.
I'm Tracy, I'm here today with Uma.
I'm the co-founder of a company called Pluto
and we're building cryptography tools for devs.
And Uma is the co-founder of
Succinct, which is building a zkVM.
So we're going to dive into some of the details
of how zkVMs work and hopefully explain them.
Uma, you want to start us out maybe with an
introduction to zkVMs and what they're good for?
Uma: Yeah, for sure.
So maybe we can start off by talking
about what does "zkVM" stand for?
It stands for Zero-Knowledge Virtual Machine.
And what that means is that if you
are used to a previous area of ZK,
typically you would write a circuit
for your computation where basically
you take your computation or function that
you want to generate a ZK proof of and you
write a fixed computational graph for
it that a lot of people call circuits.
In a zkVM, you have a program, you compile
it to some ISA instruction set and then
you prove the execution of that instruction set.
So you have a circuit that proves the
execution, in our case of a RISC-V ISA
and then you prove programs that are
compiled to that ISA instead of circuits.
Tracy: Got it.
And so that's easier than writing a circuit?
Uma: Yeah.
So the main point of zkVMs is that
writing a circuit is very difficult,
it's very annoying.
With zkVM, you can just write a program
in a normal programming language
or a ZK-specific programming language and
then you don't have to write a circuit.
The zkVM just takes care of
all the ZK stuff for you.
Tracy: Got it.
Cool.
Maybe we could get into,
I guess, like a high level overview of the
core pieces of it and how they work together.
Uma: Yeah.
So the general pipeline of a RISC-V zkVM,
in our case, is we take normal Rust code.
So you have Rust here, and you just
have totally normal Rust codes.
So for example, you can have like for --
and this is going to be some pseudocode.
Maybe I just compute like --
Tracy: The sum or something.
Uma: Yeah. The sum.
And then basically --
Yeah. So we have some normal code
and then it gets compiled to RISC-V.
So RISC-V stands for Reduced Instruction Set.
It's a small open source instruction set
with a very small number of instructions.
That's why it's called reduced.
I believe it's like maybe in the around 30
or 40 instructions, something like that.
And it's a standard target of the Rust compiler.
So you don't need to do anything to the
compiler. It's a standard supported target.
A lot of people use it for like other applications other than zkVM.
So like embedded
devices and things like that.
So we just have normal code,
we use the regular Rust compiler and
then we get a bunch of RISC-V byte code.
So your program over here turns
into something called an ELF.
And the ELF is basically like these series of
RISC-V instructions that your program gets compiled into.
And so for example, you could
have a really simple program,
and I'm just gonna have like
a few instructions here.
So, for example, one of the
standard instructions is like ADD,
and in this case ADDI stands for ADD Immediate.
RISC-V has this notion of registers
where you have, I believe,
30 something registers, and each register --
generally instructions operate over registers.
So you might have something like this,
where I'm going to add -- or let's
do actually something like this.
I'm going to add the value in the 0th register,
x0,
I'm going to ADD the constant 5, and then
I'm going to store it in the 29th register.
So that's kind of what this
instruction represents.
So I might do that again.
Tracy: And all of these concepts, these are
all traditional computer science concepts.
Uma: Yeah. There's nothing
ZK specific going on here.
And then maybe I'll AND the values
and the 29th and 30th register,
and then put it in like the 27th register.
So for example, you might have
instructions that look like this.
And this is all contained in your ELF file.
So that's like the, you know,
kind of a representation of your program
in terms of these RISC-V instructions.
And then once you have your program --
Tracy: And normally, I guess
this is meant to be run on a CPU.
Uma: Yeah.
Tracy: So like, this is a file
for a CPU
and then you're going to do something special with this file.
Uma: Yeah, exactly.
Then we have our zkVM, which basically
is going to prove that when you run this program
with a specific set of inputs,
that it results in a particular output.
And so in then our case, we take the ELF, we
run it through a zkVM, and out we get a proof.
Tracy: Awesome.
Okay. This looks good.
So this is maybe like not the
classic CPU instruction set, right?
Normally, when you make a Rust
program, you don't get this.
You get like x86 or something, and here
you're using this special instruction set
which is maybe a little easier
to use when generating the proof.
Cool.
I think this makes sense to me
And so maybe we should dive into, like, what does
it take to make a proof and an example of a proof?
Uma: Yeah. Sounds good.
So we --
Yeah. The compilation part is actually very easy,
because we're using the is like standard compilation target.
Tracy: Do you have to make any modifications to it?
It's really just run Rust with a target's flag.
Uma: You basically just run
Rust with the target flag.
Tracy: That's cool.
So, yeah, once we have our ELF, then we
actually have to do all the ZK stuff.
Okay. So maybe we can dive into how that works.
So we have an ELF that has like the instructions.
So let's go back to that world.
So the first thing we do when we have this
ELF, and this program, is we execute it.
So we have some sort of runtime, like an --
We have a RISC-V emulator.
So we have a runtime/emulator, and
we actually just execute the ELF,
and we execute each of the instructions.
One important thing to
understand here is like, you --
Or one question you might ask is, well, how
do we know which instruction to execute?
So you have a start program counter --
So you have this notion of a program counter
which tells you which instruction in the
ELF you should actually execute.
And the program counter is
literally just a number,
and then you use that number to index into
your ELF, which is just a list of instructions.
So it's really simple.
You index into this list, you grab an
instruction, and then you execute the instruction.
And so, first, you do execution
with this like emulator.
So there's the execution phase, and that's
dictated by the start program counter.
Then you basically have a while loop, that
will get the latest instruction.
So it'll fetch the instruction and then it'll execute
the instruction, depending on what it is.
And then at the end, there's a
halt instruction, or there's --
There's a way to signal that
the program is terminated.
So with --
So you generally call like halt with some exit
code, and then that's when the program stops.
So you might ask, okay, given a particular
opcode that -- or instruction that I'm executing,
how do I figure out what's the
next instruction to execute?
Typically, for example, for ADD instructions,
you just increment the program counter
and execute the next instruction.
But sometimes there's things like "JUMP".
So there --
For example, the JAL opcode
stands for "JUMP and LINK".
So this happens in like, FOR
loops and function calls,
and in general, any logic that is branching and
that will actually increment the program counter
to not go to the next instruction,
but go to another place in the code.
And so you have JUMP instructions, branching
instructions that explicitly modify the program
counter to go to a specific place in the code
and not just execute the next instruction.
And that's how we get function calls and IF
statements and FOR loops and things like that.
Tracy: Got it.
So the goal of this emulator is to kind
of do what a normal CPU would be doing
if it was executing this ELF file, but mix
the ELF file with maybe a specific input,
and then based on that, give
you like an execution trace.
Something like this.
Uma: Yeah.
So actually, the way inputs work in our program
is that we have this concept of syscalls.
So typically, even in, like normal programs,
often it's -- a question you might ask is,
"Okay, how do we get the arguments to the program?"
"How do we get the input to the program?"
So, for example, if I'm trying to prove the
nth Fibonacci number, how do I know what n is?
For us, and also in RISC-V, the opcode,
which is like, what operation is this
instruction running, is called ECALL.
And this is a syscall.
And generally these ECALLs are used
to talk to your host environment.
So your ECALL, in typical
programs, it's used to like,
you know, talk to the kernel or do other things.
Here we use it to get inputs
and also write outputs.
So this is used to get inputs and
outputs and do a bunch of other stuff.
It's basically like, you can think
of it as like special instruction.
So to get inputs into a program, we just
call ECALL with a particular syscall code.
So there's just like some constant that
says, "hey, at this point we're reading input".
And then what that will do in our -- in our
particular zkVM, is it'll just read input that
the runtime is instantiated with, and it'll load
it -- start loading it into registers and memory.
So that's how input and output
kind of work in our zkVM.
Tracy: And maybe -- yeah.
So, okay, this makes sense to me.
You're kind of like working through
this program one instruction at a time,
and you're probably logging
something along the way,
that's like building up what should be
a witness for your proof, I'm guessing.
So like what is maybe an example of a
witness look like or some execution trace,
and then maybe we can start
diving into the actual proof.
Uma: Yeah. Totally.
So, yeah, maybe this is a good
time to start talking about like
how a zkVM generally works, at
least in the current paradigm.
So, in general, I think most zkVMs today are
using STARKs, FRI and AIR arithmetization.
And so, in that world, basically what you have is
you have this -- you have like some sort of table.
So maybe you have like the CPU table.
And the goal of this STARK is to constrain
that your program is executed correctly.
So each row corresponds to an instruction.
And so here, for example
let's do the ADD instruction.
You'd have the op code, you'd have the operands.
So in this case it would be ADD --
Now, obviously, this is replaced with like a number,
a constant that corresponds to ADD.
You'd have the operands.
So in this case it'd be 29, 0 and 5.
So in this case the 29 is a register.
This is a register, this is a constant.
And then you would also have the program counter.
And then there's a bunch of
other columns for other stuff.
And really what's happening underneath the hood is that
each instruction gets
turned into one row in our STARK.
And then we want to prove that the
instruction was executed properly.
So what does that involve?
First, you have to check that the
program counter was updated properly.
And so for example, in the case of
an ADD opcode, it's very simple.
You just increment the program counter by one.
But in the case of, for example, a JUMP and LINK
instruction or you know, a branch instruction,
you have to have more intricate logic for checking
that the program counter was incremented properly.
Or set properly to the next program counter.
Tracy: Got it.
And so these --
Some of these checks probably
have to look at what happened to the registries?
What happened to the memory?
Like maybe, is there a
memory piece to this as well?
Uma: Yeah. That's a bit more
complicated and maybe we can dive into that --
dive into that in a little bit.
Tracy: Okay.
Umma: So yeah.
Basically the program -- you check that
the program counter was updated properly.
You also have to check that the memory
and registers are like set correctly.
And then you also have to
constrain the actual operation.
So you have to constrain the
actual particular opcode.
So for example, in our case, and maybe
I'll go into a little more detail here.
For example, for an ADD instruction, you have the
operands and then you kind of have the "value".
So for example, this is a register.
So these are both registers.
Register, register, constant.
It's probably a bit hard to read.
I'm just gonna --
And then, so if you -- when you have a
register, you also have to like -- you know,
take that register and look up what
is actually the value at that register.
So in our case, maybe imagine all our
registers are set to 0 at that point in time.
So X0 is 0, 5 is just a constant. It's 5.
And then after you ADD the value in X0 and the
constant 5, X29, register 29 should be set to 5.
And so if you look at these values, we do a
memory argument basically to show that,
okay -- we have to constrain that after you run this
instruction, the 29th register has a value of 5.
Tracy: And so the goal of
this procedure is to sort of
show that the machine is transitioning
correctly through each of these states,
and not violating any sort of rules
about how memory can be updated --
Uma: Yeah. Exactly.
Tracy: Or the order that memory
is touched and updated, et cetera.
Uma: Yeah.
Tracy: I see.
Uma: And -- yeah, one interesting
detail is that in our proof system,
and in general, I think most VMs
operate over small fields these days.
So, yeah, maybe we can talk a little bit
about the proof stack that people use.
Tracy: Yeah. So in this CPU table,
like these aren't necessarily integers.
They're like all field elements, right?
Uma: Yeah.
So the proof stack most
zkVMs use is STARKs and FRI.
And then they usually use a small field.
So for example, Mersenne31 or
Baby Bear, these are both 30 --
They're 32-bit primes, or I guess 31-bit primes.
Tracy: What does that mean, "small field"?
Uma: Small field.
So in general, when you do STARKs and FRI,
you can have a choice of like what prime
field you're using in these proof systems.
Historically, people have used like bigger fields.
So like 250 -- fields that are 251-bits, 252-bits.
And like in the old world of SNARKs, you
have to use those big fields.
However, I guess maybe not recently,
but in the past few years, it's become
very popular to use much smaller
fields in proof systems in general.
And the reason for that is small
fields are really hardware-friendly.
So because this field is less than
32 bits, it can fit into one word,
and therefore your arithmetic gets a lot faster.
And so your proof times get a lot faster.
Tracy: Got it.
So like, this table, instead of
being filled with really big numbers,
is filled with 2 to the 32 or smaller numbers.
Uma: Yeah, Exactly.
Tracy: I see.
Uma: So, in our particular
case, we use Baby Bear.
I believe there's -- StarkWare,
for example, is using M31.
And yeah, other teams also use Baby Bear.
So, yeah, we use small fields.
And then, yeah, we can like
go into the other things like
what our lookup argument is and things like that.
But before we do that, one thing to note,
for example here is that in RISC-V,
we use RISC-V 32-bit variant.
So in RISC-V, the word size is 32 bits.
Now our field is actually
smaller than 2 to the 32.
And so we can't keep all RISC-V values just as one
field element, because it'll overflow our field.
So what we end up doing actually is these values,
I kind of lied before or simplified before,
these values actually are all represented
underneath the hood as 4 field elements.
So you'll have values here, and there will be
4 field elements that represent each value.
So for example, 5 would be 5,0,0,0. Here
it'd be 0,0,0,0 to represent 0, et cetera.
Tracy: And this is just because you can't pack the
32-bit size from RISC 32 into the
field element of Baby Bear or M31.
Uma: Yeah. Exactly.
Tracy: Got it.
Uma: And yeah --
So then for example, now it becomes a
bit more difficult because to constrain an addition,
you have to basically do grade school arithmetic.
You have to write an AIR to constrain addition.
So you have to prove that when you
add these 2 32-bit things together,
it results in this 32-bit thing.
And there's a lot of --
That's like a very standard thing to do.
And so yeah, you often have to have extra witness columns
to constrain that appropriately and stuff like that.
Tracy: Right.
So instead of having just like
one constraint, you have several
constraints you have to check a few more
conditions, but I think that makes sense.
And then you have to do that
for every single instruction.
Uma: Yeah.
Tracy: So it does increase the cost,
I guess, of doing this a little bit, but
it's sort of what you have to do.
Uma: Yeah. So for every single opcode,
you have to basically figure out
What are the constraints, like what's
the AIR arithmetization
and what are the constraints I need to constrain
appropriately the logic of the opcode.
Most opcodes have like fundamentally
very similar high-level flavor.
You have 3 operands.
Some of them can be "immediates", which
means it's a constant, not a register.
But if it's not a constant, it usually
involves reading a value from a register.
So yeah, most operands, you load registers
If appropriate, you -- or immediates,
then you do some like arithmetic with them.
So for example ADD is adding the
2 operands and then storing it
in the destination operand AND
would do the same thing, OR, XOR.
So there's a bunch of like ALU, we call them
operations that are just doing like arithmetic.
Then there's a class of operands
that involve dealing with memory.
So like loading and storing to memory.
So that will read from memory
and put it in a register,
or take a register and write it to memory.
Then there's branching operands that basically,
you know, check if a particular value
in a register is equal to something,
greater than something, less than something, and
then increment the program counter appropriately.
And then the JUMP instructions
also do something kind of similar,
but most of the time they're just
touching the program counter.
So I think those are like most
of flavors of the instructions.
But yeah, most instructions involve registers,
and like constraining values from registers
and then doing some logic on top of that.
Tracy: Are there specific instructions
that are, like, really hard?
Uma: Yeah.
So RISC-V was obviously not
designed for being proven in a zkVM.
And so they often have pretty annoying
instructions, like, I think the multiplication --
So we actually prove a extension of RISC-V.
There's a base RISC-V 32 variant that
doesn't have multiplication instructions.
We prove RISC-V 32IM that has
multiplication instructions.
Some of those can be really
annoying, because you have
to multiply a word by a half word or you
have to multiply unsigned by signed or --
And then you have to do a lot of annoying logic
with detecting what is the top bit of a
particular result and things like that.
Yeah. So those can be pretty annoying.
Tracy: Cool.
All right. Yeah.
Maybe we'll dive into the internals of this now,
and how sort of memory attaches
to the CPU and some of that.
All right, so --
Cool. This is -- This explains the CPU super well.
I guess, there's also like,
memory and some other pieces.
Are those all represented in this one big
thing or how do those kind of fit together?
Uma: Yeah. For sure.
So let's maybe first introduce or talk a
little bit about the concept of lookups.
So I'll put it here.
Tracy: Oh, sure.
Uma: So in general, STARKs are really good.
You have this one table and
it has a bunch of constraints,
and it's proving the program
counter was updated correctly.
The opcodes are actually being constrained.
Like the values have the correct properties.
They're being ADDed together or ANDed
together, XOR'ed together, whatever.
But actually that's like kind of a
simplification of what's going on.
In practice, we don't just
have one STARK for a CPU.
We actually have many, many STARKs
that talk to each other via lookups.
In particular, we use the log
derivative lookup argument to do that.
And yeah, at a high level, what
a lookup allows you to do is it
allows you to have certain columns in one
table, basically talk to certain other
columns in another table and say these
columns here appear in another table.
So why is that useful?
I can draw it out.
So in practice we don't just have a CPU
table. We actually have many tables.
So for example, we have an ADD
table, we have a like AND table,
we have a MUL table, we have a SHIFT table.
Tracy: So you have one for
every instruction pretty much?
Uma: We have -- yeah.
We have tables for most
instructions. And what's --
Or at least for the arithmetic instructions.
Tracy: Oh, I see.
Uma: And what happens is -- and this is
pretty specific to SP1 Succinct zkVMs,
the Succinct zkVM's architecture.
So you know, other zkVMs take --
make different design decisions.
Yeah. We have this multi-table architecture.
And what happens is the CPU is actually
really lazy and it doesn't do that much.
It just takes, it takes an
instruction, it makes sure --
It loads the values, so it makes sure that like
all the registers are loaded appropriately.
And then what happens, for example for an ADD
instruction is it just looks up that a, b and c,
which are the 3 operands, appear in the ADD table.
And then the ADD table is responsible for
constraining that b plus c is equal to a.
Tracy: So you can put kind of constraint --
or like instruction specific constraints here,
and then this thing can kind of be naive.
It just has to think about what a CPU needs to do.
It doesn't really care what the
instruction specifically does.
Uma: Yeah. Exactly.
And so, this is kind of like a
very lookup-centric architecture
where the CPU is just looking
up the result of the operation.
And why is that really nice?
It's nice because in practice, to
constrain that a equals b plus c,
you actually need some extra columns over here.
So you need extra witness columns.
And you know, these witness columns are usually
for things like carries or stuff like that.
Tracy: And this is probably variable,
like different instructions need more
witness, some need just a little bit.
Uma: Yes. Exactly.
So the ADD table, for example, is pretty simple.
Like adding stuff is pretty simple.
Earlier, we had talked about the
MUL table being really annoying,
and the MUL constrains being annoying.
So the MUL table has a lot of witnesses and a
lot of edge cases and it's very complicated.
Now if we were to try to do this all in the CPU,
what we would have to do is we'd have to have
all the witness data in the CPU all the time.
And that's kind of bad because we'd have to
have all this extra area in the CPU which --
For example, when we're doing an ADD instruction,
we don't need all that extra witness data that
we might need for a multiplication instruction.
So we're kind of paying for all those
columns and all that trace area,
even though it's not being used.
With this lookup-centric architecture,
we don't pay for any witness data
or trace area that we're not using.
So it's much, much more efficient than
trying to stuff everything in one table.
Tracy: Cool.
This is actually like a pretty subtle
innovation, if I remember correctly,
because, like, these end up becoming
different proofs; isn't that right?
Like, this is one STARK, this is
another STARK, this is another STARK.
Is that how this works?
Uma: Yeah.
So this ends up being one STARK, this
is one STARK, and then another STARK.
Tracy: I see.
Uma: And then the lookup
argument just makes sure all
the STARKs are connected together appropriately.
Tracy: Got it.
Okay.
Do you have to then, like, recurse --
like somehow aggregate these STARKs
together or recursively verify them or something?
Uma: Yeah.
So if you have a bunch of
these STARKs, in practice,
what you have to do to get like one
final STARK is you recursively --
Well, you have a few options.
One is you could just have a bunch of these
STARKs, and it's still a constant size proof.
So you could just have a bunch of STARKs
and your proof is just a little bigger.
You could also recursively aggregate them
using STARK recursion, where you verify
a bunch of proofs in another proof
to get like one final small STARK.
And in practice, we do do that also
for proving larger programs,
which I think we'll talk about in a little bit.
Tracy: Yeah. Maybe this is
interesting to talk about too,
but I think, when I learned about lookups, I
was thinking about them as like a single proof.
But here you're actually
doing a lookup across proofs.
Does that introduce complexity?
Uma: Not for our lookup --
Using the log derivative
lookup argument, not really.
Tracy: Okay.
Uma: Yeah. You can also do lookups
within a single proof as well.
Yeah. For us, it's not that much extra complexity.
Tracy: Got it.
Okay. Cool.
So you have these instructions, you have a CPU.
Is there anything else here?
Uma: Yeah. So maybe another interesting
thing to dive into is our memory argument.
So actually, how does loading
all these values actually work?
Tracy: Cool.
Uma: So, yeah, maybe we can talk about that.
So, memory, obviously, is a big part of a VM.
And there's been several different
techniques for doing memory within zkVMs.
So the older technique is
known as Merkelized memory.
Basically how that works, is you have some --
You have memory. So you just have like
a bunch of addresses in address space.
So you'll have like, for example, you know,
Address 0 has this value,
Address 1 has this value.
And then, you know, you'll
have some big address space.
So maybe it's like 2 to the 32 has this value.
And then what you do is you commit to the memory.
So you basically construct a Merkle
tree of all these address value pairs,
and then you get a Merkle root.
And that is a commitment to your memory.
Now, every time you access a memory address
in your zkVM, with Merkleized memory,
you first prove that you're accessing the
particular value against the Merkle root.
So you have some current Merkle root that says
this is the memory. You proof -- You open.
So when you do a memory access, you
first open with the Merkle proof.
Tracy: So I guess, maybe briefly, just to
add context. Like the goal here is to kind
of put some structure to the memory, and
share it with the CPU or the other STARKs
that are a part of this, so that they can --
similar to what you do with the instructions,
like look into this thing and make
sure it's in the correct state?
Uma: Yeah. Exactly.
Because like, for example, each instruction
is generally modifying memory or registers.
In our case, there's no real distinction
between memory and registers.
Like, registers are just --
We just think of it as like
other addresses in memory.
Tracy: Got it.
And this varies over time too, right?
So like, you might have this entire snapshot
at time 0 and then time 1 or
instruction 0, instruction 1.
Uma: Yeah. Exactly.
Tracy: Got it.
Uma: And in the zkVM, it's really important that
you prove, "hey, when I tell you, oh, register, value",
you know, 29 has this particular
that, that is actually true.
Because obviously if you could claim
that a register has a particular value,
and that's not like a provable fact, then your
entire program execution is totally meaningless.
Tracy: Got it.
And then there's a lot of different
ways you can represent this.
And one is this Merkle thing.
Uma: Yeah.
Tracy: And I guess you're about to
share how to pull data out of it now.
Uma: Yeah. Exactly.
So you basically commit to your memory,
you say, "hey, here's a Merkle root.
That's like a succinct
commitment to all my memory".
And then when I want to access
a particular value of memory
or a particular address, I open the Merkle proof.
So I verify a Merkle proof
against this Merkle root.
Then I do whatever logic, and
then I'll update the Merkle root.
So if it's a read, I don't have to do
the second step, but if it's a write,
then I have to obviously update
the Merkle root with the new value.
Obviously this is, you know, kind of
undesirable, because it introduces this log n,
where n is like the size of your address
space overhead to every access to memory.
And so this is kind of a older technique. But --
The technique that we use is a newer technique.
It's known as "offline memory checking".
And it makes use of our lookup argument.
So what we do in our memory technique in our zkVM
SP1, is when we access memory at a particular
address and it has a particular value, we keep
-- we have this notion of a timestamp which is
basically kind of like the clock cycle of, you
know, when the instruction is getting executed.
And the clock cycle is just strictly incrementing
throughout the course of our program.
So, for example, the program
counter does not have this property,
because it can like jump around your ELF.
But the clock cycle, no matter
what, each instruction always
increments by one or roughly that.
So for us, this clock cycle,
or what we call timestamp,
is a strictly incrementing thing
throughout the course of our program.
And whenever we access a particular memory
address, and want to claim that it has some
value, what we do is we add to our log
derivative lookup argument the tuple.
And this is kind of like assuming that you
know about the log derivative lookup argument.
You add this tuple of address, the current
value, and the timestamp to the lookup
arguments accumulator with multiplicity plus
1 and you add the address, the previous value,
and the previous timestamp that you last
accessed that memory with multiplicity minus 1.
And then at the end, if you do this for every
single access, you will -- each of these will
cancel out and then you will have to check that
your accumulator for your memory is equal to 0.
And that's how we check our
memory access was all consistent.
I mean -- I think it's a bit
hard to see maybe from this.
We can go into a little example.
But maybe before I do that, one question people
might ask is how do you constrain that
an access was a read versus a write?
It's actually very simple.
If you want to say, hey, I accessed
this memory and all I did was read it,
you just say "value is equal
to previous value" for reads.
And then for writes, that's obviously
just not the case because you're writing.
So for example, in our CPU, for most instructions,
you're generally reading from 2 operands and
you're writing to the third destination operand.
So in that case we access the
memory at those 2 operands,
and we make sure that we're
reading and not writing.
And then we write to the third operand.
Tracy: I see.
So this kind of lets you efficiently
check the state of the VM as you're
going through it without -- and just
almost summing them into an accumulator.
And then you don't have to do Merkle paths,
which are maybe a little less efficient.
Okay.
And then at the end, you know
the CPU touched all of the memory registries
in the correct order and at the correct time.
Uma: Yeah. Exactly.
So --
Tracy: I see.
Uma: Maybe to go through a small little example
of this, to develop some better intuition for,
like, why, you know, you can't cheat
-- you can't make like a false proof.
Let's imagine you're trying to access
memory at some address 500. And at times --
So this is the address, this is the
value, and this is the timestamp.
So say we're time 10 and the value is 7.
And then we're at time 11. And
we're also accessing it again,
and now we want to do a read,
so the value is still 7.
And then say at timestamp 20, the
value -- we want to do a write.
So this is a read, this is a write.
And the value becomes like 15.
I also forgot to mention that another really
important thing here, is you always have to
check that the timestamp here is greater
than the previous timestamp you accessed.
So that's why the timestamp
is important. You have to --
This is a very important check.
And I'll go over why that is --
Tracy: It just means it's ordered right.
Uma: Yeah. It means that your
kind of log is ordered properly.
So, for example, here, at this point in time --
And imagine that the memory address
was initialized at timestamp 0.
And with this argument, you have
to do like a initialization phase,
where you basically just for all
the memory you're going to touch,
you just have to add it to the accumulator
at the beginning to initialize it.
So it cancels out like the first
read or last write or whatever.
So there's some subtlety there, but --
Yeah. So here we've basically added
the tuple 500, 7, 10 with plus 1.
And the previous value maybe
let's say was 0 at timestamp 0.
So we've added minus 1.
So this is like the initialization, and
that's like kind of taken care of separately.
Here, you can see that we've added 500, 7, 11
with plus 1, and we've added 500 -- the previous
value was 7, and then the previous
timestamp was 10 with minus 1.
So you can see this guy here
cancels this guy here, right?
So those two cancel out.
And then here we add 500, 15,
20 with plus 1, and we subtract
500 -- the previous value was 7 and
the timestamp was 11 with minus 1.
And you can see that this guy
here cancels out this plus 1 here.
Right?
And so at any point in time, for example, if
I tried at this point to claim that, oh --
or say at this point I was trying
to claim -- I was doing a read,
and I was trying to claim that the
value -- and I was malicious -- and
I was trying to pretend that the value
was actually 8 or something like that.
Well, I would run into trouble
because here I would have to have 8,
8, and then suddenly this guy
does not cancel out this guy.
Right?
So you --
You basically run into trouble where now these
-- this thing and this thing don't cancel out,
and then your accumulator is not zero.
Does that kind of make sense?
Tracy: I see.
Yeah, it does.
So you add this sort of fixed
functionality into your STARK,
which does this behavior on the memory accumulator
every single time an instruction is processed.
And then if anything about the memory is out
of sequence or doesn't have the correct value,
you get to the end of this, and then it's obvious
that it's incorrect because you don't have the 0.
Uma: Yeah. Exactly.
Tracy: Okay. That's really cool.
Awesome.
All right. Should we talk about --
Let's see.
So we did memory.
Should we talk about precompiles, maybe?
Uma: Yeah. Let's do it.
Tracy: All right.
Uma: So this is kind of one reason
that SP1, our zkVM is very efficient.
And in general -- you know,
zkVMs are awesome, right?
You write normal code, it gets compiled to this
normal target RISC-V, and then you prove it.
So it's kind of like, that's super awesome.
Now the downside is, you
know, it can be much more --
It can be much less efficient than handwriting
a circuit or like a specialized circuit
for your particular computation, because
there's a lot of overhead in a VM, right?
You're like reading and writing to memory.
You're reading and writing to registers.
You're doing a bunch of random operations.
And so there's a lot of overhead.
And so one way that you can address this
overhead is through this notion of precompiles.
So maybe I can kind of describe at a high
level how you can think of it conceptually,
and then we can dive into how it actually works.
Tracy: And people call these
different things, right?
There's like --
Uma: Accelerators --
Tracy: Coprocessors, accelerators, precompile.
They're all kind of the same thing,
but it's like a special circuit that is more
efficient than your standard CPU circuit.
Uma: Yeah, exactly.
Yeah. It has a bunch of different names.
So for example, for a Keccak hash function,
normally in my VM, if I just compile Keccak
to RISC-V, maybe it has 10,000 cycles.
And this is a hypothetical number.
I think it's something around that.
And so, it looks like I'm
XORing a bunch of things,
I'm loading a bunch of things, I'm
storing a bunch of things, et cetera.
So naively, it's just 10k cycles.
So that means it's like 10k rows in my CPU table.
But one interesting thing is, is if you
have a specialized circuit for Keccak,
then you can actually --
So with a precompile or a specialized circuit,
you can actually have much, much less cycles.
So you Basically replace this 10k
cycles with a specialized circuit,
and it goes down to like hundreds of cycles.
And so, concretely what that kind of
looks like is we take -- we have our
CPU here. And remember before even
I'd explain to you guys that we
have this multi-table architecture
where like the CPU is really lazy,
you know, for an ADD, it
actually just looks up the ADD.
For Keccak, we actually do something similar.
So we have a -- we signal to the
CPU, we want to do a Keccak.
So in practice, how that actually works, we use
this like ECALL which I talked about previously,
ECALL or syscall instruction, and we say,
we're going to do a syscall with Keccak.
So we're going to do a Keccak syscall, and
we're going to pass in like to a pointer.
So we pass in a pointer to the array
region that we want to do Keccak on.
So we pass in a pointer, we signal we want to
do a Keccak. And then in the CPU, we load the
pointer and then what we do is we have this Keccak
table where it's responsible for doing the Keccak.
So in our case, our precompiled
tables directly talk to memory.
So for example, here we have the
pointer, we have a timestamp,
which is like the cycle that the
CPU is going to look this up.
And then we have a ton of columns here that are
doing like XORs, that are talking to memory,
that are doing ANDs that are doing
ADDs, like whatever you need for Keccak.
And it's kind of doing it all in one row.
So, basically, instead of paying
like 10k cycles in the CPU
and paying 10k rows over here, which is a lot --
Tracy: And the CPU rows, these are really
narrow, I guess. And then these are really wide.
So you can lay out a lot more memory --
Uma: Yeah, exactly.
Tracy: And a lot more data and operations.
Uma: So normally in the CPU, our CPU I think
is like 100, 200 columns, something like that.
We hope to make it skinnier in the future.
But yeah, the CPU --
So -- you know, you have 10K rows
here and it's like 100, 200 columns.
You replace that instead
with -- it's not actually one
row. I think it ends up being like 32 rows
or something like this, with 32 rows here.
Now the Keccak table is a lot
wider. It's like 3,000 columns.
But in the end, we've saved a lot of trace area,
because we've replaced 10k times
like 200 with like 32 times 3000.
And that math ends up being
like much, much better.
It ends up being like an
order of magnitude basically.
And so yeah, the reason we can have these savings
is that Keccak table is really
wide and it's really specialized.
So it just does like XORs and ANDs and ADDs.
And then we also basically lay out the memory.
Like normally it's kind of inefficient,
because if you just naively compile to
RISC-V, you're like loading and
storing to memory all the time.
You're doing a bunch of stuff.
Here, we don't have any of that overhead.
We can just directly take the results
from the previous operation, and put
it into the next operation without having
to talk to memory. And so this is a lot --
Tracy: You don't need to like
emulate what the CPU does --
Uma: Yeah, exactly.
Tracy: To actually do this computation.
You can just like show --
You can just witness the computation
and show that it is correct.
Uma: Yeah, exactly.
Tracy: Okay.
Uma: And so this ends up being
like really, really significant.
Like it's kind of like an order of magnitude,
sometimes more gains because
you're just proving a lot less --
Significantly, significantly less trace area.
Like you've replaced 10,000 cycles
with like hundreds of cycles.
And you've replaced a lot of trace area.
So maybe like hundreds of thousands of cells with
just like a thousand cells or something like that.
Tracy: Does this impact the Rust programmer?
Uma: No. This doesn't really
impact the Rust programmer,
because in practice what we do
is you have an existing crate.
So for example, there's like a tiny Keccak crate
that's a pure Rust implementation of Keccak.
Or you have a Rust crypto crate,
that's an implementation of Keccak.
And then what happens is, we fork that
crate and we maintain a fork of it that
replaces the logic where normally you would
be just calling -- doing normal Keccak stuff,
we just replace it with this ECALL instruction.
Tracy: I see.
Uma: So we just inline the
assembly, we replace it.
And then from the programmer's
perspective, all they have to
do is they have to use our crate as a
dependency instead of the normal crate.
Tracy: Got it.
Uma: Or they can use cargo-patching to
just replace it underneath the hood.
Tracy: That's cool.
Awesome.
Uma: So it's really nice.
Tracy: Okay. Cool.
Precompiles are covered.
I think there's one other thing
that we could cover, which is,
there's this idea of long running programs.
And I've heard it called a
bunch of different things,
but I think the issue is, as you --
if you run a short Fibonacci that works just fine,
but when you start running millions and millions
of instructions, you start running into issues.
Maybe we could talk about
how you address that problem.
Uma: Yeah, totally.
So you're totally right that if you run a
short program that's maybe a few 100K cycles,
or even a million cycles, we can
just have one STARK proof for it.
We have, like, our CPU, we might have our ALU
tables like ADD and MUL and stuff like that,
maybe a few precompiles and
then you just get your proof.
But often, the programs we
want to prove end up being
hundreds of millions, if not billions of cycles.
And you can't generate a STARK
proof with a billion rows.
You're just going to run out of memory,
like it's not actually going to work.
And so for that, we have to do --
You generally have to break up your
program into segments or chunks.
We call them "shards" in SP1.
So you take your really long program
that has a ton of instructions,
you break it up into fixed size chunks
of like a million instructions at a time.
And then you generate STARK proofs of each chunk.
And then you combine each of these STARK proofs
together using STARK recursion
to get one final STARK proof.
So maybe I can draw out a little diagram of that.
Tracy: Are we done with this too?
Uma: Yeah, I think so.
So yeah.
Basically, you have --
I have a really long program, let's say.
Tracy: Does this also -- I mean, this
helps with like tons of instructions.
Does this also help with parallelization?
Uma: Yes.
Tracy: Okay.
Uma: So first I break it up into chunks or shards.
So this is Shard 1, Shard 2, etc.
Maybe each of these have
like a million instructions.
And then what I do, as you said, it's also
really good for parallelizing the proof.
I have each of my shards being proven.
And one really cool thing is,
I can prove them in parallel.
So if I have a bunch of computers on AWS or I have
some cluster, I can prove each shard in parallel.
And so the end-to-end latency
of the proof is not like:
first I have to prove this shard,
then this shard, et cetera.
The latency of the proof is actually logarithmic
in the number of cycles, which is really awesome.
So, okay, I'm proving Shard
1, I have Shard 2, Shard 3.
And then each of these has a proof.
So this is a proof.
This is a proof.
And then, the bad part about this
is now I have a bunch of proofs.
So it's not that succinct. Right?
The whole point of a zero-knowledge
proof -- well, there's two points.
One is it's zero knowledge.
So it's like privacy preserving.
Another is that it's succinct.
If I have a bunch of shards, obviously,
this isn't a fixed size proof with the length of
my computation, and we want a fixed size proof.
So what do I do?
I basically can recursively
combine two of these shard
proofs into one proof by using "STARK Recursion".
So this is a concept, and it's
pretty commonly used where you
take -- you make a proof that
two other proofs are valid.
Or in practice, you can also have n other proofs.
So you can take a bunch of proofs, we
call them child proofs or leaf proofs,
and you can combine them into one proof.
You do this a few times, you
basically have a tree of proofs.
And then at the end you get one final proof at the
end that's just -- you end up with one STARK proof.
Tracy: How big are these proofs? Are these like --
Uma: They're may be like hundreds of kilobytes.
Tracy: Okay. So you have like maybe
dozens or hundreds of these --
Uma: Oh hundreds or thousands sometimes
of these hundred kilobyte proofs,
can end up being fairly big if you're
dealing with a really long computation.
And at the end you just get this -- you
know, several hundred kilobyte proof.
Tracy: Got it.
So you could send all of these
hundreds of hundred kilobyte
proofs to somebody and they could use
that to verify that this is correct.
But instead you do these
sort of like layered thing
that gets them into one even more succinct proof.
Uma: Yes.
And one interesting thing to talk about
is recursion is very, very difficult.
So you might ask, okay, how do we
actually do this recursive part?
Naively, one thing you could do is you could
write a STARK verifier in normal Rust code,
you could basically compile it to RISC-V,
and we could use our original RISC-V VM
to basically verify a bunch of child
proofs and then generate one proof.
That's like the naive approach.
Unfortunately, that doesn't work.
We tried it.
It doesn't work.
RISC-V is way too much overhead.
It basically is computationally
infeasible to do that.
So we actually, and I think in practice,
many teams have a recursion VM.
So we built another VM that has its own
ISA, specialized for STARK recursion.
So it only has, like, instructions
that deal with recursion,
like Poseidon hashing or like,
FRI fold or things like this.
And then, we wrote a program in that specialized
instruction set to do this operation.
And so, we actually have a
specialized recursion VM over
here that is responsible for doing this recursion.
Tracy: Interesting.
Why does it need to be a VM versus a circuit?
Uma: Yeah. It can be a VM.
It could be a circuit or a VM.
Sometimes having a VM is nice
because you have extra flexibility.
You can have branching logic and stuff like that.
If you do a circuit, you
don't have those affordances.
And so, I think some teams do a recursion circuit.
We do a recursion VM.
I think in the future, we might also
do a combination of circuit and VM,
like circuit's more efficient when
you don't need the flexibility.
Yeah.
Tracy: Cool.
That makes sense.
So this is just a more efficient
circuit that lets you take what
are chunks of the RISC-V and combine
them together into a SNARK -- a STARK.
Uma: Yeah. And you also have to verify
things like, okay, the program counter.
The last program counter from here is equal
to the STARK program counter from here.
And you have to do checks like that.
Tracy: You have to link these together to
make sure that they actually follow the full..
Uma: Exactly, in sequence.
And so, you also have to do a few
checks in this recursion program that,
you know, these things are all
appropriately linked together.
Also, for us, we kind of make
use of this unique thing,
where globally -- our memory argument is
global across the entire computational trace.
And so, yeah, we kind of --
We have to do some extra things for that,
but we also have to sum the accumulator
from here and here to get a summed
accumulator across all these shards.
And at the end, we check at zero.
Tracy: Got it.
Cool.
That's really unique.
Yeah. I guess maybe from here we can talk about --
So at the top of this tree, you have,
like, 100 kilobyte proof and then typically
these are being verified on-chain, I guess.
And so you want to somehow get
that to an even more compressed
proof that you could put on-chain; is that right?
Uma: Yeah.
So typically what we want to do with this
n-proof is we want to verify it on Ethereum.
So, I mean, obviously ZK is
useful even outside of blockchain.
But a really big use case for ZK
is zk-Rollups where yo have --
you have a bunch of transactions, you
have a Layer 2, you batch them together,
and then you want to prove that the
transactions were executed correctly.
And then there is a new state route
And then what you do is you
verify those proofs on Ethereum.
And then that's kind of like how we're
scaling Ethereum, is with these zk-Rollups.
So a main target for us is
verifying these proofs on Ethereum.
Now Ethereum is, you know, very,
very slow and very expensive.
So it doesn't even like these --
These proofs are pretty small things considered.
You know, a couple hundred
kilobytes is not that much.
But Ethereum doesn't like that.
It would cost like millions of gas
to verify these proofs on Ethereum.
So what do we do?
We take these STARK proofs
and we wrap them in a SNARK.
So that's known as like "STARK to SNARK".
It's kind of like the last stage of our pipeline.
We have like our core RISC-V proving, then we
have recursion with the recursion VM/circuit,
and then finally we have STARK to SNARK.
So it's -- yeah, building a zkVM is --
you know there's a lot of moving pieces.
Yeah. So we have STARK and
then we take it into a SNARK.
And the reason for that is Ethereum has a
bunch of precompiles for the BN254 curve.
So like in particular, we use
these pairing-based SNARKs.
And we use them with the BN254 field, because the
EVM and Ethereum have precompiles for it.
So it's pretty cheap to verify
pairing-based SNARKs on Ethereum.
There's a few flavors of pairing-based SNARKs.
There's Groth16, which I think
probably a lot of people have heard of.
It's very cheap, it's very
small, it's very efficient.
And then there's Plonkish KZG,
which is basically like a -- I would
say more modern version of Groth16.
This has a circuit specific trusted setup.
So if you want to do a particular
computation or particular circuit,
you have to do a circuit
specific trusted setup for it.
For Plonkish KZG, there's
a universal trusted setup.
So you do it once, and then you can just use it
over and over again, no matter the computation.
So for us, we use Plonkish KZG.
But we can also -- we use a proof
system called Gnark for this part,
and they have both Plonkish
KZG and Groth16 as options.
But we use Plonkish KZG just because
it doesn't have the trusted setup,
which I think is kind of bad for security reasons.
And also it's just annoying to do.
Tracy: Got it.
So back here, we were talking about,
it's like FRI and it uses logUp,
and it's a STARK and AIR constraints.
And this is like a whole different
kind of set of cryptography tools.
And then when you get over here,
you need a different set of tools.
Instead of small fields, you have large fields.
And instead of maybe hash-based commitments,
you have pairing-based commitments.
Uma: Yeah, exactly.
And we -- so basically to
recurse the STARK into a SNARK,
we wrote a circuit in a SNARK
world that verifies this STARK.
So we wrote a FRI verification circuit and then
we get a Plonkish KZG proof out at the end.
And then we verify that on Ethereum.
Tracy: Right.
So you have yet another circuit.
You had like at the bottom you had your
CPU circuit, and then you had one that
combines STARKs, and now you have one that takes
a STARK in a SNARK, so you can verify it on EVM.
Uma: Yes.
So yeah, that's the whole pipeline.
Tracy: And this is hundreds of
kilobytes. And this is what?
Uma: In practice, this ends up
being like very, very small.
Like it ends up being, you know,
three elliptic curve points.
So it's like hundreds of bytes, maybe.
Tracy: Okay, cool.
And then this is millions of gas and this
is maybe like a few hundred thousand.
Uma: Yeah. It's like 200k, 300k gas.
Tracy: Yeah.
That's awesome.
Thanks for showing me this.
I think, I get it how whole
zkVM works at this point.
Maybe one more thing we could cover
is like, what are these good for?
Like what's the point of this whole thing?
Uma: Yeah, totally.
So I think ZK has a lot of use cases,
but a big use case of ZK is privacy in
blockchains and also scaling blockchains.
So things like zk-Rollups, for example,
are kind of the future of Ethereum scaling.
And I kind of described this earlier. You have
a bunch of transactions, you generate a ZK proof
that the transactions were properly applied
to some state, and then you get a state root.
You post that on Ethereum, and then you can
basically lock ETH in a bridge contract and
then do a bunch of transactions off-chain
and generate a ZK proof of what everyone's
updated balances are, and then later,
you can use that to unlock the ETH.
And so, that's kind of how a
zk-Rollup works very quickly.
And I think, Vitalik has said many
times that he thinks the end game of
Ethereum is like everyone's going
to be transacting on a zk-Rollup.
Now historically, to make a zk-Rollup,
you needed a team of like 30 people,
30 very smart cryptography PhDs who
handwrote a circuit for the zkEVM.
So Ethereum has the EVM, Ethereum Virtual Machine.
And you know, people write Solidity
and they write smart contracts that
compile to EVM and then you
needed to write the circuit
that has all the logic for transaction processing
and running the EVM and stuff like that.
And it was very complicated, it took many,
many years and it was very difficult.
And there's a lot of other downsides, like
it's hard to audit and understand what's
going on, and it's hard to like,
customize and upgrade and modify.
With a zkVM, what you can do, is you can
take an existing Rust node of Ethereum,
so for example, something like Reth. It is
a Rust implementation of an Ethereum client.
So you can just take Reth's transaction
processing logic, Reth's EVM, things like that,
and you can just import it into a zkVM
and you can run Rust code in your zkVM.
And now it becomes like kind of a
weekend project to make a zk-Rollup.
So now making a zk-Rollup is really easily
accessible to many, many more teams.
It's much more maintainable.
It's much more upgradable.
Remember like Ethereum hard forks
every six months to one year.
So every time there's an upgrade you're
just -- you know, let's cargo update my
version of Reth and then you know, oh,
I'm now still compatible with Ethereum.
And so, it becomes like much more maintainable,
much easier, etcetera with
our zkVM to have zk-Rollups.
And in general, there's like a
lot of use cases in crypto for
ZK including ZK bridges, categories like
ZK coprocessors, things like ZK oracles.
And historically all of that's been
very, very difficult to do because you
need very specialized expertise to write ZK
circuits and do all this complicated stuff.
In the zkVM paradigm, now any developer
can just use ZK by writing normal Rust.
And then underneath the hood, a zkVM team
will take care of all the hard stuff for you.
They'll worry about recursion,
they'll worry about STARK to SNARK,
they'll worry about all these constraints.
But you as a developer, you can
use ZK by just writing normal code.
And that's why zkVMs are awesome.
It just makes ZK really easy.
Tracy: I see.
I guess, it comes with some trade-offs
because like the zkEVM is this custom
built thing and the zkVM can
do kind of any Rust program.
So I guess it takes longer to compute maybe.
Or what are the trade-offs there?
Uma: Yeah. The trade-offs are that there is more
overhead. So the proof time can be a bit slower.
But in practice, actually we've found
that because the zkVM is really general,
so like it's really general, you can
support a wide variety of use cases,
it can support a wide variety of teams, you can
really put in the work to optimize it in a way
that a one specific team, who's
only doing a specialized circuit,
there's no engineering -- there's not as
much engineering ROI to really optimize it.
So basically with the zkVM, we've
actually found for a lot of use cases
that it can be more efficient than
an unoptimized circuit-based system.
Because we -- like, we have like a team of
very competent people working on optimizing it.
There's a lot of other teams
also working on this problem.
And because it's so broad, there's a lot
of ROI to making our VM more efficient.
So there are trade-offs.
It is like a little less efficient in practice.
Or sorry. In theory it's a lot less efficient,
but then in practice you're kind of able to close
that gap just because engineering is difficult,
and if you're working on improving one system that
many people use, it's kind of easier to improve.
Tracy: Got it.
Okay, cool.
Well, thanks for joining us.
Thanks Uma for sharing how zkVMs work.
It's complicated, but cool.
I think it's been a great overview!
So thanks for spending the time with us.
Uma: Yeah. Thanks for having me!